<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hidden things revealed and brought to light: or, Plain and honest dealing with Will. Lamboll &amp; John Buy, of Reading in the county of Berks, in some material queries proposed to them to be answered, &amp;c. With the rest of those that were instrumental (in too large a degree) of the former or first separation wrought among Friends here in this town, and who are found still as instrumental for the upholding and continuance of the same, by their not returning with other Friends to the ancient publick meeting-house, the doors thereof having been opened ever since the 10th of the 9th month, 1693. which is now about 9 months since, for all Friends to meet together therein, as a peaceable Christian society ought to do, in the true love, fear and worship of almighty God, that so there might be no longer two divided publick meetings held and kept up in this town, both to the great reproach of truth, and stumbling of many of the tender inquiries after it.</title>
            <author>Bonifield, Abraham, fl. 1692-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3595A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170701</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578164</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578164</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172121</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77024)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172121)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2615:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hidden things revealed and brought to light: or, Plain and honest dealing with Will. Lamboll &amp; John Buy, of Reading in the county of Berks, in some material queries proposed to them to be answered, &amp;c. With the rest of those that were instrumental (in too large a degree) of the former or first separation wrought among Friends here in this town, and who are found still as instrumental for the upholding and continuance of the same, by their not returning with other Friends to the ancient publick meeting-house, the doors thereof having been opened ever since the 10th of the 9th month, 1693. which is now about 9 months since, for all Friends to meet together therein, as a peaceable Christian society ought to do, in the true love, fear and worship of almighty God, that so there might be no longer two divided publick meetings held and kept up in this town, both to the great reproach of truth, and stumbling of many of the tender inquiries after it.</title>
                  <author>Bonifield, Abraham, fl. 1692-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: A. Bonifield.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buy, John.</term>
               <term>Lamboll, William.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Reading.</term>
               <term>Reading (England) --  Church history.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172121:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HIDDEN THINGS Revealed and brought to Light: OR, <hi>Plain and Honeſt Dealing</hi> WITH WILL. LAMBOLL &amp; JOHN BUY, OF <hi>READING</hi> in the County of <hi>BERKS,</hi> In ſome Material Queries Propoſed to them to be Anſwered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH The Reſt of thoſe that were inſtrumental (in too large a degree) of the former or firſt Separation wrought among Friends here in this Town, and who are found ſtill as inſtrumental for the upholding and continuance of the ſame, by their not returning with other Friends to the ancient publick Meeting-houſe, the Doors thereof having been opened ever ſince the 10th of the 9th Month, 1693. which is now about 9 Months ſince, for all Friends to meet together therein, as a peaceable Chriſtian Society ought to do, in the true Love, Fear and Worſhip of Almighty God, that ſo there might be no longer two divided publick Meetings held and kept up in this Town, both to the great reproach of Truth, and ſtumbling of many of the Tender Inquirers after it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>James iij. xiv, xv, xvi, xvij.</hi>
               </bibl> But if ye have bitter Envyings and Strife in your Hearts, glory not, and lie not againſt the Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:172121:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172121:2"/>
            <head>To the READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was a true obſervation of wiſe King <hi>Solomon</hi> in his time, <hi>Prov. 13.10. That only by Pride</hi> (eſpecially that which is ſpiritual) <hi>cometh Contention;</hi> and Chap. <hi>26.24, 25. And that he that hateth, diſſembleth with his Lips, and layeth up deceit within him; when he ſpeaketh fair believe him not, for there are ſeven Abominations in his Heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Is it not high time now, therefore (after ſo long ſilence and forbearance) to deal plainly with, and teſtify againſt all Deceit and Diſſimulation, where-ever or in whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the ſame is found? And, Reader, as thou wilt find plain down-right Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in theſe following needful and material Queries, ſo pleaſe alſo to obſerve how wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inconſiſtent <hi>William Lamboll</hi> and <hi>John Buy</hi>'s preſent Practices are to their former Pretences; and of all the reſt (for the moſt part) that act with them: Are they not Implicitly led to do as they do, and ſay as they ſay, and not to ſee nor act by their own Senſe, Reaſon nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, either as Men or Chriſtians, as eſpecially in this of keeping up a ſeparate and diſtinct Meeting from other Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo in many other things too large here to mention) as alſo how contrary to the bleſſed Truth they profeſs, which admits of no ſuch Confuſion, Contradiction or Diſſimulation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what ſpecious Pretences, Reaſons or Excuſes whatſoever, as they have been and are still found ingaged in? And, Reader, thou mayeſt perceive to Demonſtration, if not too much ſwayed by Intereſt, or blinded through perſonal Affection, or engaged to join with Parties more than Truth, what confuſion and contradiction theſe Men have brought upon themſelves, as by the aforecited Queries; ſo with other their Deeds and Deſigns contrary to the ſimplicity of Truth, which they in their own human Wiſdom have been and are acted in; which may be in time farther manifeſted and brought to Light, and that for the Truths ſake, and alſo for the ſakes of thoſe poor ſimple Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that have been too long beguiled and miſled by them, and others like themſelves, whom nothing leſs will pleaſe than to be Lords and Maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There will, I ſay, be a neceſſity, as kinted, of a farther Diſcovery, and more plain dealing with <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> than hitherto has been; unleſs the truly and ſincerely repent of theſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the like Evils they stand guilty of before the great God, as with reſpect to their uncharitable and unchriſtian Dealings, hurtful and evil Methods, with and towards Friends, and for the future approve themſelves as Men of Peace, by unfeigned Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which I pray heartily the Lord may grant and incline their Hearts unto, which is the worſt I wiſh to any one of them, who am a Lover of the Truth, and of all the true and upright-hearted; but as I have done, ſo hope I ever ſhall, ſtand a Witneſs for God againſt all Lies, Falſhood, Oppreſſion and Deceit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Bonifield.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:172121:3"/>
            <head>Hidden Things Reveald, &amp;c</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> I. WHerefore, and to what end and purpoſe was <hi>J. Buy</hi> and my ſelf appointed by your Meeting, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral conſent of Friends (now ſeveral Years ago) to go to <hi>T. C.</hi>'s Meeting, I ſay, and that by the Order and in the Name of the aforeſaid Meeting, to offer unto them in the Audience of the whole Aſſembly (as accordingly we did on the 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of the 5th Month, 1687. and that on the firſt day of the Week) all their Monies (of the Living) that they were out upon the Meeting-houſe, proportionable for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind and unexpired of the Leaſe, as may be ſeen (by ſuch as deſire it); yea, the very ſame Paper that we read among them as forecited and written with <hi>John Buy</hi>'s own Hand, and all this in order for the getting of the Meeting houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doors opened again, to the end we might go in and meet in the aforeſaid Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And, therefore, doth it not look (and that at beſt) but like pretence only, but not in Sincerity at all, to ſo much pretend for, but not at all intend, for either going in or meeting with Friends there, ſeeing now they refuſe and will not tho' the Doors are opened, and that voluntarily and free, without either Mony, Purchaſe, Condition or Bargain in the leaſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> II. Whether it was at all or in any wiſe according to Truth, or the gravity and ſolidity of it, or not rather on the other hand as apparent Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Diſſimulation in <hi>J. B.</hi> when we were juſt ready to leave the Court or our Meeting from before the Meeting-houſe-doors, and to take our farewel of it in reſpect to our meeting any longer there (where we had been held too to long by the reſolute Wills and politick Induſtry of <hi>W. Lamboll</hi> and himſelf) for <hi>J. B.</hi> I ſay, to ſo call the People, both Friends and others, to witneſs or take notice, that altho' we did then, or at that time, remove our Meeting and go away from that Place, yet that as ſoon as thoſe Doors (meaning the Meeting-houſe-doors) were opened again, that we ſhould or did intend to return thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again, and to claim our Rights and Properties therein; which Rights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was to go in and meet in the ſaid Houſe (and if this were not the Rights you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, pray modeſtly anſwer what others); &amp; was not this ſpoken in the Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Audience of <hi>George Whitehead</hi> and <hi>James Sparks,</hi> who with ſeveral others
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172121:3"/>were concerned in the removing the ſaid Meeting from the Court, or from before the Meeting-houſe-doors, and that had, with other Friends, the hearing of our grievous Diſſentions, publick Jumbles and Diſcord about it; that yet now, nevertheleſs, when rather intreated (ſo would come in a chriſtian and peaceable Spirit) than in any ways hindered, that neither he, they nor others he ſeemed to perſonate and ſpeak in the behalf of, will notwithſtanding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, go in nor meet with Friends there (tho happily ſome that heard him might be ready to look at it, expecting his performance of it, eſpecially under ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Circumſtances) as expreſs'd (if but to prove himſelf a Man of Truth and of his Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> III. And to what end and purpoſe was <hi>Andrew Hall, John Buy</hi> and <hi>Daniel Bullock</hi> appointed, and that by the Order and Agreement of the Month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting, to go to <hi>Thomas Curtice, R. P.</hi> &amp;c. and to deſire of them, in the Name and on the Behalf of the ſaid Meeting, either to open the Meeting houſe Doors voluntarily and freely for Friends to go in and meet together in the ſaid Meeting-houſe; or if they refuſe it, then for to offer them all their Mony that they were out upon the ſaid Houſe, both of the Living and of the Dead. Seeing that now the Doors are open'd for all to come that will, that they do yet ſtill, notwithſtanding, refuſe, neither do nor will return, come in nor meet with Friends there, though no Mony deſired for either the Living or Dead, neither in whole or in part, or any thing ſo much as like Purchaſe, Condition or Bargain in the leaſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> IV. To what End and Purpoſe was our ſo many Meetings, Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Conſultations relating to the Way and Method, what to do, and how to adviſe in the Caſe relating to the getting of the Doors open'd again, in order for our going in and meeting in the Houſe, our Addreſs to and Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation of an eminent Friend, to uſe his utmoſt Endeavours and intreat on our behalf with the K—as alſo with the C— of the ſame time by the means of a Friend that was his Baily, together likewiſe through the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſe of one as our Counſel in it, that was likely to marry his Daughter? O what Turmoilings, propoſing of Ways and caſting of Thoughts were there amongſt us, too many to recite as well as troubleſome to repeat for our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a Way and Means how to get the Meeting houſe Doors opened again, in order for our going in and keeping our Meeting there, as before, <hi>(viz.)</hi> in the ſaid Houſe; and yet how they are open'd both voluntary and free, and that without Mony, Charge, Counſel's Fees, Intereſt with any, or Influence upon any in order to obtain it, that you will not yet, notwithſtanding return, go in nor meet with Friends there <hi>(viz.)</hi> in the aforeſaid Meeting-houſe, though as cited, they are now opened voluntarily and free, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> V. And to what End and Purpoſe did we likewiſe ſo earneſtly call for and deſire the Advice, Help and Aſſiſtance of the Friends of the Meeting for Sufferings, in order for the getting open of the ſaid Meeting-houſe Doors,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172121:4"/>ſeeing that now they are opened, you will not go in, neither lay Claim of Right, nor take poſſeſſion of Property there? And is not this contrary to the Intent or End of the aforeſaid Advice and our deſiring it; for did they not only adviſe us to get them (<hi>viz.</hi> the Doors) open, but alſo when open'd to continue them ſo, by keeping Poſſeſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And was not my ſelf and <hi>William Spikeman</hi> appointed by our Meeting (and that in purſuance to their aforeſaid Direction) to open them, and the which accordingly was done by us, and 2 ſeveral peaceable Meetings alſo held and kept in it, and therefore why will you not go in now, nor meet in it, they being opened to receive you <hi>gratis,</hi> ſeeing you ſought and ſo eagerly purſued their opening before both by Mony and Intereſt; or was it well done, or Wrong or Right in the ſaid Friends to adviſe us for their opening, or in us to proſecute what they adviſed relating thereunto, or for us ſo to go in and hold two ſeveral Meetings therein, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opened? Pray anſwer and be plain in theſe things, for they are Matters of great weight and moment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> VI. And to what End and Purpoſe did you agree and appoint, as far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adviſed thereunto by the aforeſaid, the opening of the Doors the ſecond Time, after their firſt opening, as cited, and ſhutting up again, and <hi>William Lambol</hi> appointed by the ſaid Meeting to ſee it done or effected, or he to be ſo far concerned as to beſpeak an Iron Inſtrument to open them withal, if when they were, as now they are, opened, you will not, and others muſt not go in and meet with Friends there; or, if any do, to be ſo judged and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene'd for it? And were it not far better and more Chriſtian-like, in you to go in and meet there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now the Doors are open'd, the thing ſo much ſought, endeavour'd after, deſir'd and called for before, and that then as the main or principal Matter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whatever new ones you have added ſince their voluntary opening of them, ſeeing that it may be with Freedom and Acceptance ſo as cited in Peace and the Spirit of forbearance than by any of the aforeſaid Ways or Methods of the Uſe of Inſtruments, Violence or Force; and if yet, you will not (after ſo many Labours and Endeavours of your ſelves in Appearance and others for it) for how can it be thought by any that are impartial or in their right Sences, but that the contrary proceeds from your hard-heartedneſs, a Spirit of Bitterneſs and Revenge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whatever your Coverings and Pretences may be, and <hi>W. L.</hi> of all men, one would think, might have ſo much reſpect for Friends of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. (ſo over-much venerated by him formerly) to be as ready to do as to ſay, for in this caſe how can he poſſible but remember what ye aforeſaid poſitively enjoyn'd him in their ſaid Letter of Advice, and that as the Perſon moſt capable and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to do it, as he ſtood in the condition of a Truſtee for Friends on that behalf; for, ſay they, in the fore-cited, <hi>We cannot ſee how</hi> William Lamboll <hi>can be clear without uſing his utmoſt Endeavour for Friends Relief in this Caſe:</hi> Which Caſe and Relief was his getting open the Doors, in order for their Repoſſeſſing, Holding and Enjoying of their Rights and Properties therein, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172121:4"/>in the Houſe. But have we not reaſon to think, that as too good cauſe for it, That as formerly, in reality, ſo ſtill he rather diſcountenances than incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages Friends Meeting together, ſeeing now the doors are opened, and that without (as ſuppos'd) either Endeavour or Deſire of his Aſſent or Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what has been the Chriſtian Care and Labours of others in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that he yet, nevertheleſs now they will not come thither, go in nor yet appear there, to either maintain or poſſeſs others with their Rites, or to take, demand, make uſe of or poſſeſs their own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> VII. And to what end and purpoſe was our ſtanding and remaining at the Meeting-houſe Doors, and keeping and continuing our Meeting ſo long in the Court but as pretended in Witneſs and Teſtimony againſt them that were the cauſe of their ſhutting up? And hath it not been preacht publickly there, and that as point of Faith and Duty too, to be both believed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, <hi>viz. That we ought and were to ſtay and continue there, and keep our Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Court, or at the Meeting-houſe Doors until they were opened again?</hi> And therefore were we indeed to go in or not, when or if they had opened them then, ſeeing you will not, and others in your Senſe ought not to do it now? And as it may be obſerved how fabulous (though connived at) ſuch Preaching was, yet the event of the matter proved it, as it is ſtated; ſo alſo to be noted, that all theſe were but Words and mere Pretences in them, but neither Truth nor Reality, ſeeing that now they are opened, and that through the Labours and hearty Endeavours of Friends on ſo many hands both of the City and Country, and my ſelf and others in Print, that you will not yet neither go in your ſelves nor meet with Friends that do but on the contrary as much as in you lies to both Diſcountenance, Diſcourage and beget a Scruple in the Minds of thoſe that are willing and inclinable to it? All which ſeemeth to me both inconſiſtent with Truth and ſound Reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> VIII. And to what end and purpoſe had ye ſuch farther Advice again from the ſaid Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to try what might be farther done in it, by making uſe of and intereſt with the Magiſtrates of the Town in order for the getting of the ſaid houſe recorded by them for or as your publick Meeting houſe, accordingly as required by Authority for recording of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Meeting houſes in the former Reign, and thereby to engage them to be to your Aſſiſtance in the getting and obtaining the ſaid Houſe, and keeping Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it; and that in order for to keep, hold and continue your Meetings therein, ſeeing that now they are opened, and that without theſe Helps, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordings or making uſe of ſuch Men to your Aſſiſtance, you do yet, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs refuſe, deny and will not go in nor meet with Friends there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay to what End therefore were all the Labours, Troubles and Turmoils of our ſelves and others, both on the one hand and the other for their opening, ſeeing that now the thing deſign'd and intended by the truly honeſt and plain-hearted, <hi>viz.</hi> for the Doors to be opened again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is done, and you may go in if that you will or pleaſe, that now the caſe is ſo much alter'd from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172121:5"/>what it was formerly, the Cry being <hi>Open the Doors, open the Doors,</hi> &amp;c. that now open'd, the Benifit and End of their Opening is declined and deſerted by you, and to the view of Reaſon it appears that you are rather offended than pleaſed with their opening, which naturally occaſions me to add another Branch to this Eighth Query; which is, <hi>viz.</hi> How came it to paſs that you were in ſo great an Error before in all the aforeſaid Endeavours concerning their opening? for it ſeems as if you were, that now their ſuch need of ſo haſty a Retract; and may I not ſay, and that in Truth too, <hi>O what Childhood, Confuſion and Contradiction is here, for if it was Chriſtian and well done of us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly to ask Counſel and advice, and to proſecute the ſame, and that ſo far as to go in and meet in the ſaid Meeting houſe, when obtained, as in a manner by the way of Violence and Force, how can it be wrong, amiſs and unlawful now to go in and meet there, now they are open'd to us freely in a better way and after a more Chriſtian manner than by or with the Force or Strength of our own Hand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> IX. And to what end and purpoſe did we ſeem to ſo ſeek, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and incourage our Friend <hi>Robert Huttſon</hi> of <hi>New England,</hi> who did ſo earneſtly endeavour, on our behalf, the opening of the Doors, and to uſe his utmoſt Power and Intereſt with <hi>T. C.</hi> &amp;c. in order thereunto, and with the Six Friends of this Town, concerned in the like Endeavours for ſome better Accommodation in order to Peace and Reconciliation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all together again in the ancient Meeting-houſe, and in the Spirit of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance and Love one towards another, as in the beginning and paſſing by and forgiving Offences and Unkindneſſes paſt, and to be found in inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs for the time to come, by which at Two ſeveral Meetings, at <hi>Robert Paynes</hi> ſenior, matters were brought to ſo good and hopeful an Iſſue, that if not unhappily obſtructed by <hi>J. C.</hi> might have been to all our Good's, to Truth's Advantage, and whiping away the Reproach that through ſuch unchriſtian unwarineſs had been brought upon it and <hi>William Lamboll,</hi> and <hi>John Buy,</hi> &amp;c. did likewiſe promiſe (ere we would proſecute the matter any farther) That if <hi>T. C.</hi> &amp;c. would ſign the ſaid Agreement, that then they would ſign it alſo; but to what purpoſe was all theſe Endeavours, as before cited, with many more of divers kinds, ſeeing that now they have opened them freely, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that you will not, nevertheleſs, return, come in and meet with Friends there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> X. And was it not the Chriſtian Labour and earneſt Endeavour of <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> when here, as likewiſe the end of the Meeting of Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at <hi>A.H.</hi> ſo to accommodate Matters that the Doors might be opened, and that we might all meet together again in the ancient Meeting-houſe in the Peace and Love of God, and as becomes a Chriſtian Society, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as likewiſe approved of, That ſuch that were ſo minded might not be counted of as bad or dark Spirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And was not this his aforeſaid Endeavours, when here back'd with an Epiſtle of the like nature and tendence from <hi>Gilford</hi> the next day after he went from hence, and that with the higheſt Stile of Chriſtian
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172121:5"/>Obligation, <hi>viz. If there be therefore any Conſolation in Chriſt, if any Comfort of Love, if any Fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any Bowels of Mercy, fulfil ye my Joy; That you be like-minded,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>being of one accord and of one mind; let nothing be done through Strife nor vain Glory, but in lowlineſs of Mind; let each eſteem others better than themſelves; do all things without Murmuring and Diſputing:</hi> And thus concluding, <hi>The Lamb must have the Victory and Reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XI. And hath it not been your Work and earneſt Endeavours, and that on all hands, ever ſince the Doors were open'd, to get &amp; procure as many pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Friends from all parts as poſſibly you could, that in being with you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and uphold this your continued Diviſion and Separation, for doth not the Separation among us here lie now at your own Doors, ſeeing you do wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny to come and meet with the reſt of Friends, now the Doors are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they hold their Meetings as formerly, in the ancient publick Meeting Place? Doth therefore, I ſay, the Separation, as to this branch or part of it lie now in them that meet in the ancient Meeting-houſe, or in you, that uphold, encourage and continue a Meeting in another apart, diſtinct and ſeparate both from it and them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And you alſo have been obſerved to have more Viſiters ſince the Doors were open'd than happily in many Months, if not Years before: And did not <hi>John Buy</hi> acknowledge it for truth to a Friend of <hi>Hendly,</hi> and that the reaſon of it was to hold and continue the People with you (to uſe plain Words, in Diviſion and Separation) becauſe that ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, left and went away from you daily? and doth not theſe things, with ſeveral of the like nature and tendence, found upon you, plainly declare you to be the very Womb of Strife, Authors of Diſcord and Mother of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Separation amongſt us here in this Town and place?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XII. And were not you, <hi>viz. W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> the chief Inſtruments and occaſion of the firſt Separation in our monthly Meetings, for Buſineſs, when together, and that long before that the Doors were faſtned up, and which I am apt to think was none of the leaſt occaſions of it? for did not you divide, go away and ſeparate from them, as the like by us ſince, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that upon no other occaſion than their altering of the Place of the Meeting, <hi>viz.</hi> from one Room to another, that is, from the upper Room, where it was formerly kept, to the Meeting-houſe Room below? And was not my ſelf denied by <hi>William Lamboll,</hi> &amp;c. and that many Years ago, at one of your monthly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to be a Member of the ſaid Meeting, or to be in any capacity for to do or act as ſuch, and that barely and alone becauſe diſſatisfied with, and could not be one with you in ſo wilful and reſolute a Separation, looking upon the Provocation to be but ſmall to excite to ſo great and unchriſtian an extream? And did not <hi>John Buy</hi> propoſe, at one of the ſaid Meetings, for a Minute to be made in the monthly Book, That whatever I offered, or had to ſay, no body ſhould ſpeak to me, or take notice of it, or give me any anſwer, ſaying; <hi>That if they could not bind or tye my Tongue that they would their own?</hi> therefore to what degree of Pride are theſe Men arriv'd, that have ſo much cried out againſt Perſecution, and impoſing on others that are now for Binding or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172121:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:172121:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:172121:7"/>up of Tongues, if they could or had Power in their Hands to do it, (though as far as they have they have us'd it, and that to the utmoſt) the Tongue being the principal and moſt intelligible Inſtrument of my own or any other Man's juſt and innocent Defence? I ſay, to what degree of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, Oppreſſion and Perſecution this Spirit of Tongue-tying, impoſing on and Conſcience-binding hath arrived unto, though from a ſeeming ſmall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, the mournful Cries of the Sufferers under it have loudly ſounded forth through every Age? And laſtly, and to be moſtly lamented of all, and that if it could be even in Tears of Blood, that it ſhould be thus found even as from and amongſt our ſelves, as hath been expos'd too publickly by our Friends, the Sufferers in <hi>America,</hi> from the Hands of <hi>Loyd, Cook, Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay hath it not come in time to the tying and binding of both Head, Hands and Feet alſo, and in proceſs of Time too to the uſe and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of the Gag, whereby the Lords Innocents have been forc'd to ſtand as mure and dumb under all the Cruelties and falſe Accuſations of their impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Adverſaries, as if guilty, and that at laſt not ſufficient neither, but the Coat and Hat of fearful and affrighting painted Devils, Hell and Hell Fire put upon them, when ready to encounter the Flames for Righteouſneſs and a good Conſcience-ſake? Well Friends, what a great Flame hath ſo ſmall a Spark, or little Fire kindled, and how far this of either yours or theirs might have burn'd, had not the want of Power and Opportunity prevented, God only knows. And bear with me, for I cannot but be plain in this Matter, for the Zeal of the Lord burns as a Fire within me, againſt all ſuch Cruelty and Impoſition, though in its leaſt and ſmalleſt degree, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where ever, or in whomſoever it is found, and that it is no other than the Root of Perſecution, Womb of Cruelty and Mother of Blood-ſhed and Inhumanity, as has been clearly and evidently manifeſted from the effects thereof, and that in every Revolution of Time, Age and Generation, and how far ſhort of the aforeſaid, the Gag and Fire excepted, this Lording and impoſing Spirit hath manifeſted itſelf likewiſe in our Days by that common ignominious Badg or Mark, caſt on us by ſome, <hi>viz.</hi> of Troublers, wrong Spirits and out of Unity with Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> towards ſome; and that for their Fear and tender Conſcience towards God, let them judge, ſpeak and tell, that have known, felt and long born the Weight and heavy burthen thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XIII. And was it not your earneſt Endeavours with <hi>O. S.</hi> and others, in party with you, that as ſoon as you heard that the Doors were opened, or to be opened, to make all the Party you could both in Town and Country; in order to prepoſſeſs, fill and fortifie the minds of Friends againſt the Thoughts of Reconciliation (unleſs upon your own Terms, as reaſonably could not be thought would be condeſcended unto by <hi>T. C. &amp;c.</hi>) or that which in ſome degree might be in ordes unto it; which was a Chriſtian Mind and Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them to meet altogether again, with Friends, as formerly, in the ancient publick Meeting-houſe, in the tender Love of God, and Spirit of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172121:7"/>Forbearance and forgiveneſs one towards another? I ſay, hath not this evil Work of continuing the Separation been eagerly carried on, managed and promoted by you, and that with Diligence, yea and great Induſtry, both in private as well as at your quarterly Meetings, and the ill effect of the aforeſaid, as thus managed by you, now brought forth to more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick view, contain'd in a Paper, ſtiled, as from the quarterly Meeting, ſign'd by <hi>O. S.</hi> with a Poſtſcript annexed by <hi>W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> and directed and ſent to the aforeſaid <hi>T. C.</hi> wherein is raked together and brought up all the old former Matters relating to both the Occaſions, and particularly of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which ſeemeth clearly for Aggravation rather than Peace, Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by ſo exacting of them the utmoſt Farthing; I ſay hath it not been your Work, ever ſince the aforeſaid, to raiſe up and lay as many Mountains and ſtumbling-blocks in the way as poſſible you could, in order to ſtop and prevent Peace (if juſt-ſpirited Men, that know the true Lines, and meaſure by the right Ballance of the Sanctuary, you ſometimes make mention of as a Cloak to cover and hide your ſelves under from Judgment and Shame, be your Judges) for whoſoever reads or views your ſaid Paper may clearly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that inſtead of intending it in order for Reconciliation that you have rather made an abſolute Fence and Defence againſt it, or any further Thoughts concerning it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for was it your former Cries to, or demands of them, O open the Doors, burn your bad Books and condemn your evil Actions, for ſhutting of them up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or was it <hi>John Buy</hi>'s and my Meſſage or Commiſſion from you or the Meeting, to the aforeſaid, as mention'd in the Firſt Query, to tell them of Condemnations and Book-burnings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or <hi>Andrew Hall</hi>'s or <hi>Daniel Bulloc</hi>'s either, when ſent by the Order of the Month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meeting unto <hi>T.C. &amp;c.</hi> as cited in the Third Query? or was our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Order or Demands more, or any thing further than only for them to open the Doors for their Friends to go in and enjoy their Rights and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties in the Houſe, and to excite them thereunto, to both bid and offer them in Mony very conſiderably, as both my ſelf, <hi>J. B. A. H.</hi> and <hi>D. B.</hi> do full well know; and therefore whatever is added more, is beſides, over, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove and beyond our former or firſt Propoſitions to them; and therefore to be ſuſpected as the Work and Contrivance of the above-mention'd <hi>O. S. W. L.</hi> and <hi>J. B.</hi> in order to obſtruct Peace, carry on and continue Diviſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XIV. And was not your impoſing on my and other's Conſciences, with denial of my ſelf and them an equal Right and property, in the way of Purchaſe, with you, in your new Meeting-houſe, as great or a greater Evil than the faſtning up of the Doors? And hath not the forecited, with what elſe remains (and lies at preſent as dormant concerning you) of as bad or worſe a Conſequence ſhewed you to be full and altogether as faſt and as hard, if not harder, ſhut up againſt my ſelf and others in your Hearts, though without any juſt Cauſe for it, than ever the outward Doors were, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And do you not remember what cannot be ſo eaſily forgotten by ſome, <hi>viz.</hi> what an
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172121:8"/>Unchriſtian, Unequal and Unjuſt a Superiority, Injunction and Spiritual kind of Teſt was projected, managed and carried on by you, <hi>viz. W. L. J. B.</hi> &amp;c. both againſt my ſelf and others, who could not be wrought upon to be ſo tame as to bow our Necks to any ſuch Evil and Antichriſtian Yoak of yours, in your ſuch binding Impoſition and lordly way of Inſulting over my ſelf and them, and that for only witneſſing againſt what's ſo plain and apparently wrong, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And why were not thoſe weighty and neceſſary Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſent you about it, <hi>viz.</hi> relating to your Clandeſtine Under-hand Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Deſigns and Evil, as well as Arbitrary Management of Matters relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as cited, to your ſaid new Meeting-houſe; which may rather be called, as things have been thus unjuſtly unchriſtianly, managed by you, a Houſe for Strife, Diſcord and Contention than in the leaſt for Peace and the Worſhip of God, anſwered by you before thoſe ſo often repeated and continued Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries and Exclamations againſt others, who at the very ſame time were acting as bad Wrong, if not far worſe, your ſelves, and that deliberately, which makes ſome diſtinction, and aggravates your Sin, and that highly too? And why were you ſo ſhy and mute before <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> at the Meeting at <hi>Andrew Halls,</hi> when he ask'd you, What you ſaid to thoſe Queries then propoſed? which were but a little part of the whole, and which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily yet again ſee the Light, with the reſt of them, unleſs you change your Ways, be humbled and repent, and turn from theſe and ſuch your fond and lying Vanities, to fear and ſerve the true and living God? And although it be granted, that they did not do well in ſhutting up of the Doors; yet on the other hand, How can it be that you or any of us can be excuſed or did well to give them the occaſion that provoked unto it? And, as for my part, things being weighed in the true and equal Ballance, I cannot but impartially conclude and ſay, <hi>Let him that hath been wholly without Fault therein cast the first Stone at his Brother;</hi> for was not yours and others impoſing on them, and over driving in matters relating to outward Orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a great, or the greateſt occaſion of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XV. And have not my ſelf and others, as well as you or any of you, ſtood in our Teſtimony and Witneſs for God againſt all, that in any, wherein I or they have thought ſuch to be wrong or acted contrary to the Truth in any reſpect (and do think, and for my own part may ſay) and that to the full too, if not in too forward a Zeal, exceeding my Bounds in it, as you your ſelves have done, of which, if you think it not your Intereſt to be thus naked and plain in the matter, for my own part I think it to be mine, though not for any ſelf end or Applaud of Men, God knows, but the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of a good Conſcience towards him, being neither afraid to own, nor aſhamed to ſtand by and juſtifie what I have thought and do ſtill believe to be juſt and right; nor on the other hand to diſown and condemn whatever either then or ſince I do believe or am ſenſible either was or is wrong, whether through Ignorance or otherwiſe, and do hope that I may and ſhall ſtill do the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172121:8"/>like for time to come, in whatever may yet appear to be contrary to God, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and the Holy Truth that we profeſs, however thus evilly handled by you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XVI. And whether if you ſhould be plain-hearted, naked and ſpeak the Truth, that the main or chief cauſe of your obſtinacy, in refuſing to come to the ancient Meeting-houſe, and to meet with Friends there, be not for fear that then you may be in danger to both lay down and loſe your Crown, and be ſhortned in your Power, ſo as that you could not any longer exerciſe ſuch a high and lordly Power over others of your Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as hath been your long and frequent Practice toward them, and that for this ſeveral Years, even to the making or occaſioning of another or ſecond Diſcord or Diviſion among us, and that ſince whilſt a part by our ſelves and from the others, or long before they had opened the Doors for us to meet altogether again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that as great a one too proportionable to our number, as was wrought in the firſt or former Diviſion in this place, with the like evil and bad effects, and unchriſtian practice of keeping on the Hat in time of Prayer to Almighty God, with the like diſturbances, oppoſings, breakings up of Meetings, <hi>viz.</hi> both on me and others, and Confuſions hardly in any point or thing ſhort of or inferior to the former, together with moſt bitter, ſevere, cruel and hard-hearted Words, Sentences and Expreſſions, both in Teſtimony and Prayer hard to be thought of, as uncomly to be heard in a Chriſtian Society, towards any, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe of the ſame Faith and Perſuaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XVII. And now you having got a Meeting-houſe, and that by your own means procured, and according to your own Wills have managed the ſame from firſt to laſt; have you not framed to your ſelves a deal of Comfort and Satisfaction? And are you not, as it were, at your Hearts-eaſe therein? Are you not very loath to be diſturbed, ſo as to remove from thence? And do you not conſult more your own quietneſs and eaſe, than a publick Good, or the promotion of Truth in the general, or the exaltation of the pure divine. Power and Seed of Life over all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> May it not be feared that you will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be much inſtrumental (in the Minds you are in) ever to promote the work of Truth in this place or elſewhere, eſpecially as with reſpect to a Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation one with another, to the repairing of Breaches, that have and do ſtill continue to widen them ſo much?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XVIII Whether it may not conduce more, both to the Honour of God and of his Truth, and likewiſe tend more to the Reputation of us as a People, to be kept in Peace as a Chriſtian Society, rather for you (and ſuch like minded with you) to continue where you are by your ſelves, than to come in ſuch an irreconcilable or prejudiced frame of Spirit, as too evidently you manifeſt your ſelves ſtill to be found in; and ſo thereby the cauſe of freſh and new Diſturbances, and if not of worſe Confuſion and Diſtraction, than formerly?</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:172121:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XIX. Is it not ſad we muſt needs ſay ſo, That becauſe of your not coming, and for your ſakes, Friends ſhould be deprived of the benefit of the Labours and Teſtimonies of publick Friends, who labour in the univerſal Love of God for the Good of all? And are they not prevented many of them upon your account, from coming to the ancient publick Meeting-houſe, where they might (as I conceive) have a far greater Service among ſo many that come thither, being, as I ſuppoſe, at leaſt three to one of convinced People and others, to the ſmall number that meets with you?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> XX. For truly Friends, to be naked and plain, the beſt adornment of our Chriſtian Profeſſion, when I ſeriouſly weigh and conſider of the many ways, means, endeavours and contrivances uſed by you, in appearance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the opening of the Doors, it naturally occaſions me to place ſome Remarks and Obſervations upon it, <hi>viz.</hi> That notwithſtanding the thing deſired, and ſeemingly ſo earneſtly ſought for, <hi>viz.</hi> the Doors to be opened, is now obtained, and that both voluntarily and free, without either Means, I mean as from you, or Charge, Help, or the Uſe of any of you, that you ſhould yet notwithſtanding refuſe to go in and meet with Friends there, and take, make uſe of, or injoy what ſeemingly was the Main and Tenor of all your Pretences. Indeed, it makes me amuſed, as well as difficult to find out, what you did or do really intend, deſign, or would be at; for was not the opening of the Doors the chief and principal Matter inſiſted on? Now done, for the Doors are now opened; what you ſought, is ſo far obtained; what you asked, it is ſo far given; and what you expected, is ſo far performed; and that yet for all this you appear as far from Satisfaction or Content as you did before: In plain, as if nothing you demanded or ſought to have done, were done (were at all yours) or ought to be taken notice of by you, tho' the main or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal of your Demands, as cited, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore, what can one ſay, or how may I conclude, but that every part, yea, all, and the whole of all, was but Shows, Words and Pretences only, but neither Reality nor Truth in any of them all? and, therefore, may conclude, and wind up the whole Matter in this my laſt Query, <hi>viz.</hi> How can it poſſibly be that ſuch things as theſe ſhould be well pleaſing to God, or at all, in any wiſe, conſiſtent with the Truth and his Will, that is ſo vaſtly wide, ſo untrue, and altogether inconſiſtent with it ſelf?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:172121:9"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Doubt not at all but that I may be both apprehended, thought and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged of by ſome to be too plain as well as too particular in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Queries and Inferences thereupon; but as in my Title Page I do affect Plainneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo I have (and who can anſwer to God for me if I do not obey him?) more cauſe to be plain to theſe Men, than happily many do know of. But this, in ſhort, for the removing of all Scruples wherein I can or may, from ſuch as are truly conſcious in them; to ſuch let me, therefore, further add, write and ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> That both the preſent Age and Time, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and Occaſion, requires Plainneſs. And, in truth, my Eye, and the Eyes of all that are truly ſingle and upright to God, looketh not ſo much at the Praiſe or Approbation of Man or Men (a Snare, and that a great one too, altho' ſo taking with ſome in this Age) as to or in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon to Peace and a good Conſcience in his ſight; for this I can (and that truly) ſay, as in the ſight of him too that is the alone diſcerner and ſearcher of all Hearts (whatever any proud or exalted Perſons may imagine of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves he is only ſo) that the aforeſaid hath been both my only end and aim, and the occaſion of my being thus far concerned at this time with them, and to ſpeak as I find it to ſpring and riſe in my Heart, ſo let me ſay, O Friends, the time is come, yea, high time, and the full and ſet time and ſeaſon (after ſo long ſilence and forbearance) to be plain and ſpeak, yea, and to Tell, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, and to Preach too, and that upon the Houſe top, what hath been long hid and kept ſecret in the dark; for as <hi>Solomon</hi> well ſaith, <hi>As there is a time to keep ſilence</hi> (but that time is going over) <hi>ſo there is a time to ſpeak,</hi> and that time is come; and to bring the ſecret Work and Works of Darkneſs to Light; tho' as one once ſaid, That the very Eye-lids of the Morning are unto ſuch Workers as the ſhadow of death, tho' the Children of the Day rejoice in the Light, and in the Day, and ſeek not after darkneſs or the ſhadow of Death, or the Night to hide and cover themſelves and their Deeds under; but on the contrary, rather deſire that as their own, ſo alſo that all Mens Deeds may be both brought to, and be tried by the Light; for the Light diſcovereth all things, and is True and is no Lie, neither changeth as Men change; and in it hath the honeſt and ſincere hearted truſted even unto this day, who have not ſought themſelves nor their own Glory, but the Lord before and above all things: Elſe had they and ſuch been overcome, confounded and brought to nought long before this day. But oh! Glory and Honour, true and everlaſting Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172121:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>be given to and returned unto him, who is the God of Truth, and Lord, yea, and the only holy one in <hi>Sion</hi> this day, who is alone able and ſufficient for theſe things, and a help in the needful time, on the behalf of ſuch that are poor reject of Men, and of no Might, yet found to be the Lords, and of a broken Heart and contrite Spirit in his ſight, whoſe Groans and Sighs have been heard in his holy Ear, and mine and ſuch's Tears is put up into his Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles. I ſay, Praiſes be to his Name, for that he hath been and is the help of true and ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in this needful, trying and ſhaking Day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Men have forſaken the true fear of the Lord, and the proud Boaſter hath lifted himſelf up a time indeed; in which may it not be ſaid as <hi>J. B.</hi> did ſome Years ago (ſo but rightly explained) <hi>viz.</hi> In which a wrong Spirit hath entred the Camp, the Fruits of which is it not ſpiritual Pride, Partiality, Impoſition and Oppreſſion? And is not this the accurſed thing found therein, and like to <hi>Achan</hi>'s Wedge of Gold and Babiloniſh Garment, which cauſed <hi>Iſrael</hi> to fly before their Enemies, as altogether unable to prevail or ſtand before them? The Lord purge it out from among us, and that ſour evil Leaven of the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> which as Chriſt our Lord hath ſaid, <hi>Is Hypocriſy</hi> (and great and deep Deceit too) <hi>whatever Men may ſay or do profeſs;</hi> a little of this Leaven, in whom it is found, we ſee is too apt to work and infuſe it ſelf into the whole Lump. So having thus, in ſome degree, eaſed my ſelf, and diſcharged my Conſcience for the preſent relating to theſe Things, I ſhall commend them to the Conſciences of all Friends, but more and in particular to the truly judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and innocent Ones, whoſe Conſciences are impartial, and truly tender to both God and Man; and ſo do remain (as I truſt ever ſhall) a Lover of the Truth, and of all ſuch that keep their Habitation in the innocency and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of it.</p>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Queries, with what elſe is annexed to them, are intended for to go among the Profeſſors and Friends of Truth only, and no others.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Bonifield.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172121:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
